the uh the guided meditation it should
be or meditation in general be it guided
or not it should be about
understanding person should not be
looking for um
special novelty experience to come out
of
it it should look for clarity and
understanding they will then obviously
if done rightly result in Freedom from
suffering and
peace so whether person is just
meditating for 10 15 minutes or
dedicating 5 hours a day it doesn't
matter what is that that time is spent
towards establishing the mind in
Clarity of experience of the nature of
experience that's why the
instruction is necessary if you if uh if
you don't know what you what to look for
if you don't know what to
discern you won't find it by
yourself so even as the guided meditation goes it
so even as the guided meditation goes it
should be
guiding towards understanding as you
often read about it in the
sutas let's say that um that a person
does want
to settle their
mind without falling into sort of
mystical absorptions but without over
rationalizing either so the first thing would be
either so the first thing would be
Solitude physical
Solitude physically removed from other
people far enough to not hear them far
enough to not see them far enough to not
feel that you can be encroached by them
at any given time so secluded and
remote once you're secluded in remote ask
yourself what is really what is the goal
of the practice what is what is
my specific purpose what am I trying to
achieve am I after happiness am I
after peace am I after freedom from
suffering are all these things so sort
of merge into one one goal that I want
to
achieve whatever the answer may
be it should be clear that the answer is
not about that
about that
experience being given to you the answer
is about that experience being developed
the experience of peace happiness
freedom from suffering and so on so you
develop it by knowing what you're
supposed to
develop that's what with said he measure
he goes and listens to the wise people a
man goes in with the wise people then he
reflects upon what he is so that he
measures the
task so measuring the task means knowing
what you need to
do and all the tools for freedom from
suffering are already contained within
your experience as a
whole within the five
Aggregates as the would have said the
reason for suffering is
craving reason for freedom from
suffering is the extinguishing of
craving and craving is not to be found
elsewhere it's not in things you crave
for it's not in things you're attached
to it's not in things that uh that you
find there in place it's not in the
world it's not in the object of your
senses it's not in the object of your
attention it's in your eth atude towards
things that you can attend perceive and
engage
with so if you were to remove the
craving gradually if you were to stop feeding it
gradually if you were to stop feeding it
if you were to allow it to fade away
through non-maintenance
then the result is freedom from
suffering again within this very present
experience as a whole not before or
after right now
so having gone to secluded Place away
from people probably take some time for a
people probably take some time for a
mind to settle in into that
Solitude whenever that
is without overdoing it without over
attending it just start regarding
yourself as part of that non inhabited
setup you are part of that remote Forest
cave root of a tree a Hut whatever you
might be there are trees there are
be there are trees there are
rocks there are rivers there
waterfalls there is your body there as
well there are monkeys there are birds
there are snakes there is your body
there as well you are not separate from
it and the reason why why it's important
to start reflecting like this because
the whole
point of
um apprting the craving is through that
non-maintenance as I just
mentioned and that non-maintenance
is um developed and
discerned when uh when you realize that
you can't maintain it even if you want
to when you realize that the very
Foundation of your own life is not in
your own control you have no say in it
your life is a secondary byproduct of it
your choices decisions you've been
making are secondary to
it and that's nothing other than
impermanence that the Buddha was talking
about so you
reflecting that in your solitary setup
like in this case this cave here this
cave in huge tree trunks broken trees
broken rocks um split side of the mountains and
rocks um split side of the mountains and
so on your body is
actually closer to those things than it
is closer to your point of
view your body belongs to these rocks
and trees and um forests mountains and
so on belongs as in it's it's it's made
of the same elements so the whole your
of your body as in my it's completely
gratuitous the only reason you can
regard your body as yours is because
there is something to to be regarded as
mine and that something precedes your
ownership that something precedes your
your appropriation of this is mine so
that's what you're reminding yourself of
that's what you're well maybe reminding
yourself or Discerning It For the First
Time doesn't matter the solitary setup
free from people free from this
disturbances where you are alone left on
your own
devices you start to see that your own
point of
view is actually um almost almost
incidental in a grand scheme of things
grand scheme of things
of the
entire four great
elements the mountains the forest that
you are in your body
shares that nature your body is
that which
means as these great rocks I mean they
they're huge yet you can look and see
even they break down split and
they break down split and
crumble and what then is to be said
about this human body of quite a soft
soft form soft
form soft
composition mild in comparison to these
Granite mountains but if the granite
mountains even they cannot
escape the the the gradual destruction
what is to be said about this very soft
body and this is not not for the purpose
of some kind of um poetical musings or
or romantic Notions no it's undermining
your own very sense of existence of
which is basically your own very sense
of control Mastery and ownership so it's
not necessarily going to be pleasant
especially not if it's discerned for the
first time these things are frightening for
time these things are frightening for
those who still
want to hold on to their appropriated
point of view as the owner of the body
and so on that's why people would
sometimes freak out in the suts when
they would start to comprehend
this and that's why you learn how to
find peace in it it's really optional
fear is optional you don't have to fear
it but you will automatically fear it if
it contradicts your point of view of of
ownership which you're refusing to let
go of so you're gradually undermining
your own sense of ownership whereby well
even the fear cannot be on so you stop
being afraid but you do have to accept
you do have to go into that direction so
this very
body 6 feet tall
surrounded by Wilderness belongs to the
Wilderness that belongs to the great
planet Earth that belongs to a complete set of
Earth that belongs to a complete set of
its own laws and circumstances and
accidents and and change of elements and
so on which means not even a tiny bit
tiny grain of
this human body can be mine actually can
obey me the Beating Heart the muscle the
pumps the blood completely invol
voluntarily is like these um these
Rivers flowing here the the trees
growing and so on but if something
little changes those great things will be gone
changes those great things will be gone
what is to say for a little inferior
tiny muscle in your chest that pumps
blood that keeps you alive basically or
lungs being still able to breathe the
movement of the wind in this Forest the
movement of the Wind on the mountain the
movement of the wind within this body
that's it so again that's why the Buddha would
it so again that's why the Buddha would
talk about these things in the sutas you
you are to to reflect on it so that you
actually
feel as not in
control so that's why the virtue needs
to be established beforehand you must be
dwelling restrain and keeping the
precepts because if you start
undermining your own sense of self your
own point of view which is all about
control and Mastery well you start
undermining your sanity very often not
always but very often because that fear
can overwhelm as it happen many time in
the sutas but it can't overwhelm you if your
sutas but it can't overwhelm you if your
behavior has been purified beforehand as
the Buddha would
say so by dwelling in the solitary
environment free from others you
actually get to see that whatever
personality whatever sense of self you
have created in the course of this life
it's fully dependent upon this living
operating organs of this body that are
on the level of trees rocks rivers
mountains and so
on and when those things come to cease
so these organs will also come to see
they cannot possibly remain
standing so it's not a it's not a
question of of looking for a great
Epiphany or or or some great revelation
of the Hidden truth the question is of
clar find this very image this very
reflection maintaining it and letting it
endure letting it exist peripherally
while you go and do other things
establish your mind in it because you're
basically establishing your mind in
non-appropriation you're establishing
your mind in the impossibility of
appropriation cuz it Doesn't I mean you
don't think twice about these branches
and stones and here if somebody were to
ask is this yours does this belong to
you the answer is no of course not but
if somebody were to ask ask you about
your own body you'd say well it is my
body or you might stop and think about
but it isn't in the same manner these
objects around you in this
Wilderness accidental
Forest that's also your body shares the
same nature none of this is yours and their
nature none of this is yours and their
body cannot be yours because if it were
yours you would be in charge of your own
heart the way beats you could tell it to
stop you would be in charge of your own
um metabolism your own lungs brain and
so on but you aren't any notion of
control intentionality and choice that
comes to you it's secondary it's fully
within the container of this given
body which means when that given body
ceases to be given to you all the things
that you do on account of it will not be
able to stand anymore so
anymore so
seclusion in order to stop identifying
yourself with people with external sense
of control with external sense of
management but
instead as stepping back into something
greater something more accidental
something that's that cannot be
conceived to be controlled
such as
Wilderness and then maintaining that not
expecting a u a
great bolt of lightning when every
answer is given to every single question
no just maintaining that very setup
because that very setup it's basically
puncturing the bubble of of of of of
craving and it's slowly bleeding
away that's what I meant by
non-maintenance of it you can't stop
maintaining it overnight but you set up
the environment that prevents that
cannot give rise to maintenance of
craving of one one's own appropriation
and that's how craving bleeds out Fades
away then even if you with people
afterwards there will not be the
induction reinduction of your own
ignorance and your own
appropriation so giant Roots massive
rocks huge benon trees great
mountains large
rivers yet all that is accidental what
is to be said about the blood flowing in
this body the heart pumping the lungs
breathing I mean probably even these
small trees and branches are more
durable than this body body is yet
somehow this body is regarded as mine as
in my as it is in my
control as if it is in my
control so it's not about denying your
sense of
control it's about undermining it while
it is still present so there is me there
is this sense of I am but you want to
undermine it by seeing it fully
determined by that which cannot be yours
that's how your own s of control ceases
to be yours that's how arahan can still
act talk choose prefer without actually
owning anything cuz he has fully
surpassed it surmounted
it because the only reason people
appropriate things is because they don't
fully understand that they cannot do
so I mean I can say yes this mountain is
mine but it's completely meaningless
it's even meaningless to me I know it's
meaningless and there is no amount of self-induced
and there is no amount of self-induced
conviction that will make me believe no
it isn't mine it cannot be mine this
this planet Earth is mine yeah sure but
you know that that that that statement
is hollow well it's not more Hollow than
saying that this body is mine it isn't
it's absolutely on the same
footing and if that is discerned then
yeah it will be equally meaningless for
you to think that this body this heart
this lungs this this um these senses is
a
mine and then there will be no problem
left for you to deal
with cuz you have
surmounted let go of extinguished the
basis of all problem so you don't go
around dealing with every single problem
individually you just uproot the basis
for any problem to arise